this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean recently launched
spaces a beautifully simple object
storage service designed for developers
who want a simple way to store and serve
a vast amount of data such as images and
large media files user-generated content
backups and logs spaces is available for
a simple $5 per month price that
includes 250 gigabytes of storage and
one terabyte of outbound bandwidth
additional storage is priced at the
lowest rate available one cent per
gigabyte transferred and two cents per
gigabyte stored this provides cost
savings of up to 10 times along with
predictable pricing and no surprises on
your monthly bill try it for free with a
two month trial by going to do dot co /
se radio welcome to software engineering
radio my name is Brian Romero our Sinha
is VP of engineering at transferwise an
international money transfer platform
harsh was director of product at PayPal
where he led the product strategy and
development of PayPal's mobile apps and
software development kits harsh also
spent 10 years at eBay starting as a
software development intern in rising to
a head of software engineering harsh is
also an advisor and an investor in
early-stage startups welcome harsh to
software engineering radio thanks for
having me Brian today we're discussing
product management which deals with the
planning delivery and marketing of a
software product will discuss how those
functions are achieved and how product
management interfaces with engineering
to begin I'd like to ask what is product
management so product management is a
multi-faceted discipline basically the
way I think about product management is
all the tasks needed to take an idea a
fledgling idea to the strategy of
execution of that idea the execution
with the team to bring their power to
life to the customer and then the lather
rinse repeat up the process where you
learn from the customer
and then iterate on the idea and improve
the product so the ownership of that
entire process is usually done by an
individual in a team who's called a
product manager so it's a it's a
function that it's not just a one-time
function where you're dreaming up new
products it's as you say iterative that
it's a cyclical process of planning
definitely what are the responsibilities
of a product manager so I would break
down the responsibilities of a product
manager into three main themes the first
one would be recall inspiring inspiring
from a perspective of having an idea if
you're working at a company let's say
it's a startup or a large organization
usually the company has a larger goal or
mission statement or you can call it as
a vision of the company from there you
as a product manager have to think of
ideas work with the team work with the
customers to understand what do you need
to build to add more value and align the
product towards that vision of achieving
the goal that is initially set by the
company and that is requires a lot of
inspiration getting inspiration from
customers but then also inspiring the
team within to build this product and
under inspiration I would say there's a
lot of work around understanding the
market understanding customer needs
understanding how your current product
is placed along with other products and
competitors in the market and what is
the real true value proposition that
you're providing to the customer so the
way I think about it is in this phase
you would think about answering the
questions which are what is the problem
you are solving what does the customer
why does the customer care about this
problem that you're solving and why does
it matter to the customer and who does
it matter to along with this in the
inspiration process you would also have
to define success and failed carrot
criterias for everything that you
launched so if you're going to run an
experiment to test whether a new feature
is going to add value or not to the
customer experience before you even
think about writing your first line of
code or getting anything done you could
define and work with the team to
understand what would be the success in
Philly failed criteria so that is kind
of the umbrella of the inspiration part
and thinking about the ideation of the
product the second part which is a big
role that a product manager plays in a
team is prioritization so product
managers tend to get feedback from all
different places they can feedback from
the customer as I said before they look
at the analytics and what the market is
doing they look at what a competitor's
did doing they also get feedback from
the team as to what's possible to build
and not to build in the overall product
lifecycle and taking all this data and
feedback helping the team to prioritize
as to what are the next top things to
build what are the next top things to
get right as a products evolving is a
large part of the product managers role
it doesn't mean that the product manager
goes into a conference room by
themselves or in a cube by themselves
and just puts the head data and
prioritizes across an Excel spreadsheet
but it's more about having the dialogue
and having the harder conversations with
the team based on scoping sizing
possibility of building what is desired
right now in the market was is where the
technology can do all that input has to
be taken into helping eventually the
team have a conversation to come out
with a prioritized list of things to do
and the third part of the
responsibilities of product manager I
feel our execution so nothing gets built
with the strategy execution is we need
strategy for lunch dinner and breakfast
so
execution is a very critical part of
product management and from my
perspective the big things that product
managers tend to execute on and have to
be good at is of course defining the
product specifications based on the the
first two parts of the ownership that I
just described which was inspiration and
ideation and then prioritization second
part is not just defining the happy flow
but also defining the unhappy flow and
the edge cases when the product would
not work I would not work as always
desirable third part is kind of being
the
project manager to an extent of making
sure things are getting delivered and if
there are blockers that are impacting
the team some of this could be outside
the team then helping drive those
conversations crossed him across the
company to make sure those blockers are
removed so that the team can move
forward and finally in the spirit of the
learn build measure learn process making
sure the analytics are set up correctly
read correctly interpret correctly to
determine whether the experiment or the
learnings our success or failure and
filling that back into the iteration
cycles so that the product keeps
continue to be iterated on and improved
that's how I see other responsibilities
responsibilities of a product manager
are I see so there's these multiple
phases that that you have to discover
what what the needs of the customer are
then again articulating those needs to
the the team the engineering team to be
executed and then and then the job is
not done
at that point you've got to help see it
through to execution and then deployment
and then even at that point the job is
not done you need to gather metrics to
determine success degrees of success and
and then start the process over again
yes so an interesting question it would
be
why should this job be done by an
individual product manager are there
cases that would be easier just to have
customers talk to the engineering team
directly so that's a very interesting
question I transferwise specifically we
tend to do this so we believe in having
as few people between the customer and
the engineers as possible so we have set
up cases where engineers take a customer
calls directly working with our CS
agents engineers answer emails and chats
directly and the idea here is to not not
basically have the engineers become CS
agents or become the person who's just
talk to the customer but actually trying
to give the pain the feeling of the pain
that the customer is going through to
the engineers and
when engineers are building something
and building the product they understand
the why why they're building part as
they're shipping stuff that said there
is only so many cycles in a day it's
only hours in a day and engineers do
have to execute and write the code and
develop the systems that drive the
product and write the experience and
probably fishin see perspective also it
is good to have one person or a group of
people who can actually collate talk to
different folks whether its customers
with its partners with its other if
you're in you know b2b business other
businesses who can then tell you what is
it that they want and they still that
down to a few larger themes that then
the team executes zone also that it's a
little bit of a skill set question here
too like for most engineers it's not
always natural to be able to get out in
front of customers and be able to speak
their language and understand the
specifics of the requirements that they
are asking for because introduced a lot
of times tend to be a little bit more
involved in the technical details of
things so a product manager can also act
as a good translator and a medium to
convert those customer voice into actual
internal implementation specifics but
overall we do push transfer wise to have
engineers speak directly to customers
yeah I imagine that avoids some items
getting lost in translation or having
the needs or pains that the customer
somehow changed by a game of telephone
definitely that's the main reason why we
do this yeah yeah so generally speaking
it would be then for a mistake to to
think of the product manager is a person
that should be filtering or somehow
being the conduit of communication from
the customer to the engineering team
it's always it sounds like it's a it's
always better to have that kind of a
customer access or at least being able
to understand the customers needs and
pains yeah definitely so is that before
like I think the product matters rule is
to clarify and explain the why and the
what of the problem and then let the
engineers figure out the how but
how do you do that in a manner such that
you don't take away very specific
details that the customer shared so that
what the voice of the customers really
carry carries to to the engineering team
it's important
is there a document a formalized format
that a product manager or product
management should provide that
articulates the customer pains what in
this process of discovery what is the
product management provide to the
engineering team to to clarify and
categorize the customer pains yeah so
I've worked in and worked in different
size organizations and built different
size teams so I think it varies a lot
from organization to organization how
structured this is so I've worked in
teams where you know product managers
write down specifications in Word
documents and then it goes through
multiple reviews and peer reviews before
it makes it into the engineering
engineering teams inboxes seems to be a
much more traditional approach and I'm
sure the organization's running that way
even now I said remember back in the day
when I was at eBay in the early days
they used to be a template of a document
called a PRD a product requirements
document and that literally was the
template used by every product manager
in the organization that would be
answering a bunch of questions on every
feature that was proposed to being
launched and it was a full-on you know
40 pager kind of document where you
would have screenshots or wireframes and
everything specified in that and then
this would make it to the engineering
manager or the engineering team and then
there could sue that interpret the
document into an ERT which was an
engineering requirements document which
was even longer and which talked to the
took the part of the crime was
documented with technical implementation
details to that before it actually went
into the full implementation process for
the product now what I just spoke about
is a much more waterfall lifecycle of
developing a product this is when we
used to take you know a few months to
ship
at least nowadays the way we see teams
working and product specifications
working a much more higher level so I
can give an example of how we work on
this and transferwise in trance we tend
to run smaller product teams so we
usually have one product manager with
about anywhere between three to six
engineers on a product team and these
four our teams are full stack so we'll
also have CS people CS representatives
Customer Support Operations
representatives if we need to have a
business partner or a banking person
given within financials that person's
also on the team and overall the team
plans together and prioritize this
together and understand why they're
building what they're building and the
product specification usually starts off
in ticketing system like JIRA which
would be starting with an epoch which
where you specify what are the main two
tasks and the major what is the main
theme that you're trying to achieve here
and what is the main value prop and from
there then the epics broken down into
specific tasks which are iterated on by
the product team so that's how basically
it's set up now so having smaller teams
and usually one or two location teams
that work well across hangouts also
helps drive that conversation where you
don't have to write as many documents
battery there's an iterative process so
the feedback loop is going faster so it
the financial team may be part of the
the product team does that mean that the
team that product managers or product
management interfaces when the product
team is a cross-functional team very
much transyl wise we've completely
Abernathy full stack admits a
cross-functional team of having all
disciplines that's needed to get that
part of the product life is that
difficult to achieve in still maintain a
small team I think it varies but in
general so an example of customer
support so of course if you launch one
part of the product let's say
transferwise has a we have a product
which allows you to move money between
us to the UK
so there'll be a core team of customer
support in individuals who are
supporting that route so we would not
have the entire team in the stand up and
the planning sessions but you'd have a
representative one representative from
that team who understands the scope and
the challenges the customer support team
and the customer interactions is
creating to give input to the team so we
tend to have some representative
representatives for larger teams but
then the core engineering team and
product team will be there so usually
this one product match and futures will
see so it sounds like the the process at
each iterative cycle of managing the
product developing the product the
customer is an important aspect of the
process especially for the
responsibilities of product management
why is the customer so important I mean
I guess in this product driven world the
way we we're here to solve customer
problems if we just are building stuff
without getting input from the customer
then it's probably more of a hobby
project or or a project with its you're
trying to do something where you're
trying to learn a new technology or do
something which is very specific to your
needs but given that we are here to
solve customer problems having the
customers voice and the customer input
and feedback throughout the process to
understand what's working what's not
working is super important else teams
can drift very quickly based on their
own assumptions so one thing we see
quite often is anecdotal evidence being
taken as the direction as real evidence
it's the whole thing of you know people
thinking their problem is the biggest
problem to solve so if you are moving
money between US and UK and you see a
specific behavior that is true for you
and your friends ten friends around you
you think that the world's like you as
opposed to having feedback from the
larger group of customers so moving
money on transfers between US and UK and
then taking their verbal feedback and
quantify scores on the feedback that we
request and making decision that's
that's what's important to make sure we
don't get the bias of just you know the
unconscious
simile buyeth of the context of just
working in your own to solve your own
problems in in the case a new product is
being developed how do you get that
feedback when you don't yet have
customers you're maybe exploring whether
this project is feasible how do you
understand who your customer might be
yeah that's a very good question so new
product development cycle is a little
different than reading an existing
product usually again you would start
from the basics like I mentioned before
so you're trying to understand what is
the problem you're trying to solve and
why would a customer care that you're
solving this problem why does it matter
to the customer who are the other people
who are solving this problem is it
actually are you solving problem number
forty on their list as enough of my
professors in Berkley Steve Blank would
say or I you solving problem number one
two three and it's very important
because as I said before a lot of times
we tend to think if we have this problem
a specific problem that's the biggest
problem to solve so whenever you're
doing a new product development there's
a lot of time you to spend around
researching whether it actually is a
problem in the market that the market
requires to it's a big enough problem
that the market needs to be solved
currently and one of the things that you
look at is to see how our customers
solving the problem right now
what is the offering that exists in the
market right now and then you try to
think about could I build a product
which is an order of magnitude better
than what exists in the market this is
where you hear things like it's a 10x
better is it 50x better but the idea is
the same whether it's 10 or 50 but is it
an order of magnitude better that
solution that you're providing to your
customers then what exists in the market
if it's only 20% better if it's 10
percent better the probability of a
customer switching or changing the
entire workflow it's very very low and
it can be a very very big uphill battle
to acquire users so once you've done
this kind of thinking and understanding
what the market is what is the problem
you're solving why would the customer
care to scatter what they cried enough
to switch that's when they start think
defining the successor fulfill criterias
you start thinking about what the flow
would be you start doing certain bits of
user testing so this is more qualitative
work where
you develop wireframes or mocks and you
try to get out there and talk to
potential customers so it's very in that
process you also identify who your
potential customers would be so getting
out there you know buying somebody a
coffee at Starbucks and sitting down if
it's a consumer facing product and
actually working through the process of
understanding explaining the product to
the customer and see if they're getting
it do they understand the value
proposition with the things that this is
something that they would use this they
think that this is something that they
would pay for those are the things that
you try to iterate and learn very
quickly in the early phases without even
building any any product in any tech on
any code and from there then of course
you get more evolved you start doing
some basic prototypes and I used to
something up with a small small
application and see how people use it
try some traffic to it that's kind of
the iteration of a new product process
so in the idea of user cases is that
something that would go in the PR do but
would be would be some of the things
that I would find inside of an example
PR D yes use cases would definitely be
things that would go into a PR D just a
general flow of what you probably are
solving and how would the customers
solve that problem with the car with the
partnership building so that's that's
definitely something we'll go into PR D
that would include use cases edge cases
defining for each use case what would be
the successful criteria and then going
deeper into understanding how would you
even set up analytics and what are the
things to track to make sure that
eventually as the product goes live
you know what the parameters were and
what the markers were or what the
attributes were that you were testing
for how is that fed into the reporting
engine all that stuff would be defined
and is it important to you have a
description of the customer like a
profile in that document as well yes so
different teams to dis differently some
people define it as customer personas
some define it as like an ideal user but
having some kind description of who you
solving the problem for is very
important so we have the P that
describes the use cases the customer can
you give me some examples of the
analytics that would be useful the these
analytics would be metrics for measuring
the success of the product what
what kind of things would be would we be
looking for so some of the basic
analytics would be things like let's say
you started a new product you try to
understand how many people are landing
to see that product or seeing the
product landing page for example or a
home page or if it's an app than the
home screen like how many people are
actually visiting as I would say to
explore the product and from so you
would start looking at like non logged
in or session based visitors and then
you would basically build out a regular
conversion funnel so if your product is
something that requires in the end
somebody to take an action and there is
a whole process of converting that
person from a visitor to eight an actual
signed up and registered user to
actually in the first transaction so
I'll give you the example of
transferwise again for us a user is a
user once they've created the first
transfer and completed the first
transfer that means money has moved on
the platform if you've just signed up as
a user and you've created an account
given us an email address and set up
your account but you haven't created and
funded your first transfer and the money
hasn't showed up at other site we don't
count you as a user yet so now through
this whole process this conversion
funnel let me look at so we look at
somebody who lands on the hour let's see
our website landing page as a visitor
then what did they do as interacted with
the page did they how much time did they
spend on the page that they scroll
around they interact with certain
components certain elements of a page
which explain what we do how many moves
what is the value proposition that you
have we have a calculator on our home
page which tells you the basics around
if you were to move a thousand US
dollars to pounce how much money would
you get in the end on the other side in
UK what would it be the fees so did they
play with that calculator if they did
that means that there is some intent
that some engagement and from that
process then you will start and seeing
where do they fall off if they do fall
off and leave the platform before they
complete the first transfer so did they
fall off if they clicked on get started
which is on a calculator which takes you
to our signup page from there did they
go into that page and fill out the
username and
email it really was the email address
and so at the account then did they go
into the flow of creating the first
transfer which is a step by step flow of
giving us details of how much money you
want to move what is your current
information
what is the recipient information and
distracting this entire process of
making sure where the user is where the
user drops off did they have
difficulties are errors in filling on
any of these fields how much time to
spend these are some of the metrics that
you would actually to understand how the
product is doing eventually the success
of feel of this product would be things
like as I said before did how many users
of the total number of users visited the
site converted as in exited the funnel
with converting to create a new transfer
so and then these are measuring metrics
like what is the conversion rate it is
10 percent is it 20 percent is it you
know 35 percent and from there then you
understand
what are the things that you can improve
to increase that conversion rate so they
could one level deeper into some of
these analytics numbers that I talked
about our metrics I talked about whether
they're getting dropped off at the
registration page did they get an error
that they spend a lot of time on the
home page but then dropped off there did
they interact with certain components
that's how you look at it so it's
probably of course the case that each
different product is going to have a
different set of metrics but generally
speaking the the reason that you're
collecting this data is to improve the
product to understand the user better
and see where the product is fulfilling
the needs of the user and where it's
failing to yes exactly
so this would also lend me to think that
the as you gather these metrics and
process this information that gets fed
back into the PRD and it may change the
user stories that you originally started
out with the PRD becomes a living
document it's it's there's a feedback
loop in there is that correct yes it
depends again on the organization and
how what processes exists in the company
so that's a transpose we don't do as
much PR jeez but we work more in like
more agile manner with epics and tasks
but then the idea being the same that
given the feedback and
and the analytics what the numbers are
showing this is feedback would flow back
into new requirements whether it's in
the form of a PRD iteration it's in the
form of a new epoch new stories new new
plants it varies based on the company so
yeah it seems like the processes is
designed to it sounds like the the
process is designed at transferwise to
be able to iterate quickly and reduce
friction so that rather than being on a
periodic or your cyclical in nature but
you're not periodic in nature it's we
have a continuous yes and also we push
our set up such that once a product's
life even in the early stages of the
product being developed engineers are
much more closely involved with that
understanding the wives just like a
product manager would and ideally the
way we iterate then after the products
live is the engineers are very much into
the analytics in the data too so then
they can read the data and try to make
assumptions and like making inferences
and understanding what's working what's
not working because a lot of times
you've seen that with that input the
iteration speed can be even faster
because the engineer has actual data to
interpret and work through and then
iterate the product quicker and in that
case the product matter then takes the
step of takes the seat of role of
coaching the engineer and interpreting
the data and like moving along the
product and you should there's more
engineers than a product person on a
team so if you think about every feature
that's life if they're more engineers
who take ownership of this feature being
life in production the iteration speed
increases because it doesn't have to go
to one person who's a product match I
was interpreting all the data and giving
instructions to the team on how to
things along it's an important
distinction so in the in the case then
that this feedback is arriving the
analytics the the team is processing
these analytics that the tickets are
generated if they're a triage process or
that goes directly back into the the
backlog how is that how is that
processed yeah I mean usually that's how
teams would operate here again we don't
believe in having
we believe in solving the problems that
the teams have so every team kind of has
their own slight modifications of
process as opposed to having one single
process for the entire company so the
wave most teams in France why does it
work
is the feedback would come in that would
go into some form of a backlog in the
form of tickets and then usually teams
run on a one week or two week errands
most of the teams here don't know one
week cadence and before the team would
go into planning for what they're going
to achieve with you on Monday morning
for the week usually the product lead
and team lead the engineering team lead
but they get together and do a quick
triage so that they don't spend as much
time in the planning session with where
it's a larger group of people explaining
and discussing some of the
prioritization work but they will pick
up things that have already been
noteworthy from the previous weeks and
been that in the backlog and drop some
of the other stuff that may not be as
relevant so that way you have a
efficient use of the time during
planning in the iteration for the next
week all 0 is the easiest and fastest
way to implement authentication and
authorization architectures into your
apps and api's allow your users to login
with username and password social and
enterprise identity providers such as
Facebook Twitter ad or office 365 or
without passwords using slack or
whatsapp getting started is very easy
use one of more than 40 SDKs and add a
few lines of code no credit card
required get the free plan at auth0 io /
se radio that's a u th the number zero
io / se radio oz0 is trusted by
developers at Atlassian Mozilla
Optimizely and Financial Times try it
out at our zero dot io / se radio and
get back time building core features can
you tell me what a product roadmap is
and given your process do you use
we have the definition of park roadmap
for us is a little bit more like a
vision document I would say so every
team again operates a little differently
we launched something recently called
the borderless account so the borderless
account is a new type of virtual bank
account that we
where it allows businesses and consumers
to hold balances in different countries
and different currencies easily and then
you can get paid and payout as a local
person in all these countries so people
in cross 20 different countries can not
just sitting in their own country open
an account in the with the USD currency
or a UK currency and they also have
local US UK bank account specifications
so you could be sitting in India and you
could have a US bank account with a bank
account number and routing number and
now if you're a freelancer then you can
get paid locally in that buy account
number and routing number which is a big
deal for a lot of people because if
they're doing business cross-border then
when the clients are paying that gives
when the issued and they give the
invoice in the local u.s. re number and
account number they seem more legitimate
they are more trustworthy and also the
pair doesn't have to deal with dealing
with cross-border transfers and stuff
like that so now this process and this
product is pretty new for us we launched
it about five months ago and for that
there's much is a bigger product roadmap
which is like a vision document and then
that breaks down into different phases
and in those phases as you go out
further in like say phase 1 phase 2
phase 3 the phase 3 would be more
nebulous with higher-level problems that
we try to solve for the customer but
then phase 1 phase 2 which we would be
right now in we'd have be linking would
be linking into this kind of backlog and
this kind of JIRA dashboard that we were
talking about where you have all the
epics define and more of the new term
tasks defined clearly so it sounds like
the product roadmap is perhaps more
important for projects that are just
kicking off or at least a new phase of
the an existing project or product yeah
I think it's fair to say I think the
vision document definitely is very very
important as you start off a new new
phase or a new product and it still is a
living document so as you evolve the
product it should have some of the
changes and iterations in it but it's
very very important
the initial phases to understand the
entire scope of what you had trying to
build and what problems you're trying to
solve
so in each of these phases obviously I
guess the phases marked it to some area
of time
phase one being the near term goals
phase two midterm goals through phase
three far horizon what kind of items
would be inside of each of these phases
what would you describe in each of these
these portions I guess that's uh I live
into the to the product and an
implementation strategy so in our worlds
like given we're a fast-moving consumer
product usually the near-term like phase
one would be if it's a new new launch
product it would be the basics of
getting something up and running as an
MVP so minimum viable product which is
has to be the usable product but it
solves the core customer problem and
it's very important to get that out to
understand how would a customer use it
and how the customer find this product
and knowingly that we know there's a lot
of features that are not there yet all
the bells and whistles on there but it's
a usually product for those people who
really have the problem in the market
right now the most and they might still
pick it up and use this product in its
MVP form because they're willing to take
the pain of using this because
alternative is so bad and from that then
you would get more feedback from these
early users and early adopters to see
what is working what is not working and
then incorporate that feedback into the
iterative cycle so that could be a
larger face-to-face fee and that's how
to go so I guess an important aspect of
defining what the MVP is is something
that's practical usable valuable to the
the customer or user but also don't go
too crazy because you want to get it out
there to get the feedback from the
customer so yes definitely who is the
roadmap written for who is the audience
of the roadmap that's an interesting
question I think it varies a lot across
companies in most cases the roadmap
consumer the audience is
team so the team that is going to
implement and build the product I think
it also spans outside the current
implementation team so it could be other
teams that possibly need to get need to
help you get this product to the market
it could be other teams who need to
understand the impact of you building
this product on their roadmaps or on
their product and then in a lot of
larger companies a lot of times the
roadmaps are also the audience could be
different stakeholders or like you know
senior leadership but usually the
roadmap is and the audience for it would
be the internal company company
employees who are helping build this
product so it's very very important that
the team at least buys into understand
by them to the roadmap and understands
the nuances of what's in phase 1 phase 2
phase 3 and then it spans out from there
the further you go away from the team
the roadmap probably gets more higher
level 4 for people it sounds like
because product management is a
cross-cutting concern if you will or
spend so many different teams that the
roadmap that's developed should take
into consideration is is there a support
team or customer success team that needs
to understand the product what what
product is going to be coming certainly
I would imagine that sales would like to
know the four forthcoming features and
what the product is going to be that's
useful for them as well definitely here
so it so anybody who who has involvement
with marketing I would imagine also is
another important audience of the of the
road band yeah so they said like you
know different teams who are not inside
the implementation team but possibly are
impacted their work is impacted either
what their building is impacted or what
they're selling is impacted what their
marketing is impacted what they're
supporting as in like supporting
customers calling in is impacted all of
them would be consumers of the roadmap
and they would like to know where the
product is right now when it's going to
launch one of the features so again
taking a look inside of that product
roadmap we would see at each of these
phases I guess it's different for
different cultures different companies
different organizations but it would it
be like a list of
teachers at each phase is but it include
the user stories
does it need it be that detail product
roadmaps
I think operated a little bit higher
level and and see what we've been
discussing before around PR d--'s some
of them for a new product might have
user stories or at least personas to
give an overview or high-level overview
for the problem we're solving but in
general roadmaps from there very quickly
go down to here the main things that
we're going to launch and those things
are basically capabilities that the
users will be given after the product
launch so will they be able to do XY and
Z that's where the roadmap covers the
level of depth the roadmap usually
covers we've we've done our customer
interviews we've we've done our research
as to what the product should be and who
we're servicing what users were
servicing with the product as we go into
implementation the agile team
cross-functional team that is
implementing the product or implementing
the project a lot of these functions
seem to be fulfilled by the product
owner of a vas chrome team is there is
the product owner the same thing as a
product manager or the same functions
other circumstances that they're
different people and if they're
different people how do they interact
usually in my experience so far the
product owner and the product manager
the same people at very rare cases if
for example it's a very technical
project or product change it might be
the changes owned by the technic
technologist in the team or the
technical leader in the team but in
usual cases I've seen is the ownership
lives on the product manager to
eventually bring the product to
production or to the live environment in
front of customers this is true for both
consumer products and b2b products that
I've seen in the product management is
being achieved by the product owner what
degree should let me rephrase that one
more time if I may in the case that the
product manager is interfacing with the
product owner what interaction would
those have with regard to prioritizing
the backlog let's say for instance
so privatization is a very big role for
a product manager to do well in the team
way we operate and the way I've seen
teams in general operate privatization
is a two-way conversation it's
definitely not something that's just
earned by the product manager product
owner the way it works is basically
having an open conversation around what
is the customers expectations so that's
one of the inputs that goes into the
prioritization process like what is the
customer what is the customer problem
that we need to solve first before we
get to the later problems so try to
define the initial MVP but then also
there is quite a bit of input around
what is technically possible to build so
it could be the case that while there is
a big feature that the customer is
asking for building that specific
feature in the initial version might be
technically much more challenging or
might require quite a few quite a might
it longer than the other features and
it's the song and dance that happens
between the technology team or the dream
team in the product team and understood
understand what will be the initial
prioritization to get something out that
is still usable that customers would use
and we could learn from and take the
feedback that I thought was pretty cool
you say the the technology team and the
dream team the dream team being those
that that would request new features and
have a have a stake in the vision of the
product is that is that correct
oh sorry maybe I misspoke I'm in the
engineering team added to the dream team
but but I guess that's true there would
be a dream team I mean they shouldn't
really interesting we have a process for
developing a product we have a process
for implementing the product and even
getting feedback and metrics to see how
its performing how can a product manager
been it has some responsibility for the
business success of the product it seems
to me would you say that that's correct
yes
so in tricky situations where something
kind of comes out there's a new customer
they they would like functionality and
perhaps they would like this
functionality prioritized in the backlog
or the roadmap or it's something new and
it's a big account I can see that
there's a there's kind of an inherent
with needing to fulfill the needs of the
customer but also as you say that song
and dance of the balance of what's
technically achievable
how can product managers help mitigate
that conflict or deal with it you know
when there's there's things that come
out of left field that disrupt the paint
the plan yeah I think this is one of the
biggest struggles that a park manager
has to deal with as they work with the
team and build up with the product so I
don't think there is one specific way to
handle this I mean you obviously have to
weigh the pros and cons the trade-offs
for every discussion and decision one of
the things that I've seen especially in
the case of what you specifically
described which sounds like more like
b2b case like got a consumer product but
more like a business product or SAS
product where you could have one large
customer who could really just you know
impact the entire growth or revenue or
the growth of the product overall in
this case I think it's important to try
and see whatever you do build today for
this customer is that actually going to
be used by other customers I think
that's a very big litmus test have
you've seen a lot of products and I've
seen this in my in my career that tend
to make optimizations or changes for one
large customer and large customers also
10 can make a lot of promises and then
you implement something and something
goes out and then they might still move
on to some other product or they might
not see the value of what you built as
much as you initially thought or
promised so it's important to make sure
in the largest group of the vision of
the product or the roadmap that you have
and the other customers you have how
does this like you know I guess spending
a lot of time for the specific team to
build this new feature how does it
impact other customers could you turn
around and sell it to others if that's
the case and that's true for a decent
majority of your customers that I think
still is a better conversation to have
then basically just selling and
disrupting an entire running product
team's roadmap for one once
if ik left-field I use kiss but I guess
I said before it's proven core analysis
how much like in front of its keys for
example now we have obviously very
driven by how much volume
our platform is pushing and how much how
many users we being onto the platform so
it would be a trade-off to say if we
want to do if you were to do X as
opposed to a B and C which was already
in our roadmap how much time would it
take what would it what would you have
to drop and what is the value that we
perceive of a B and C bring into the
business as opposed to doing X and
probably in the in the next
retrospective after having gone through
a situation like that worse a pivot
needed to be made to facilitate business
need for a potential customer and their
respective you would probably examine
that and say could we have mitigated
such a thing by being maybe a little bit
more check our alignment with our
customers are we doing the right
research and I would also imagine that
the benefit of having the customer
interact with engineers reducing that
barrier means that the engineering team
can also be able to understand this
requirement that it won't feel like it
came from left field and they're able to
pivot a little bit better because they
do understand that customer need
definitely so yeah that's very true and
that's why we believe in like getting
engineers closer to the customers and
the customer problems and understanding
the why and the big part here is also
because when you're building that part
of the system of writing that code if
you kinda know that this is the kind of
requirements that might come in the next
five six eight months then you think
about that as you design these systems
to be able to be extended and to be made
not required to be a very hard coded or
built for as only one specific use case
no it's it's often said with regard to
the both the responsibility and maybe
even the role of a product manager
product managers are often said to have
a lot of influence but not very much
authority what does that mean have you
heard that expression before what does
that mean yes
he's funny I
I've heard the suspicion of like the
product manager is the CEO of the team
and I actually don't believe that's very
true in a lot of ways usually the CEO of
a company for example has a lot of
authority in the company and could you
know could make hire and fire decisions
in a lot of ways that doesn't apply for
the product manager the part with the
part which might be true is the
inspiration piece so usually in a lot of
cases in most companies the ceos tends
to be people who've been the initial
founder of the product or at least are
in seen as the inspiration who's driving
requirements in the strategy at the
overall company level and the company
vision and from that perspective I do
think product managers biggest role is
to inspire and lead from inspiring and
influencing so there's this thing that
we talked about an transferwise the
engineers we hire there are teams called
product engineering it's not just
engineering and as I've said before
earlier in the podcast push engineers to
get closer and closer to the customers
to understand the whys of what they're
building and engineers in our company
had the right to walk from their team or
vote with their feet when they believe
that what they were working on doesn't
anymore help the customer the transfers
customer as much as working on something
else so in that setup the product
managers role is even harder because
they need to explain and have the voice
of the customer front and center and
really inspire the engineers to be doing
the best work in in moving this product
forward and then I think that's where
having the ability to be able to do
storytelling or likely be able to be
very clear in communications and
bringing the voice of the customer into
the room and be able to explain the why
and the what is very very important
because you don't have authority gives
power usually across your team so that's
interesting that because especially in
your case that engineers can elect to
participate in a project it's it's the
case that a product manager product
owner should not only
act questions may be healthy in
arguments about the product and the
features but also invite it as well yes
very true in fact if you're not having a
healthy discussion or a debate about
what you find to build then maybe maybe
you're not getting enough people
interested in to the problem that you're
trying to solve which eventually would
lead to possibly not having a lot of
people working on it with you so that
aspect to the healthy debate that also
implies that there's probably some soft
skills involved with this role and
responsibilities that in order to keep
the debate healthy and productive and
not being a personal argument but maybe
a more loyal ally argument for lack of a
better term you're arguing for a
solution not for a position is what I'm
saying that requires a certain set of
soft skills that are important
definitely I mean if you look at product
managers successful product managers
they've definitely very good they're
high in EQ and they're very good on
being able to assess the situation in
which different people are interacting
and be able to move the conversation
forward around solving a customer
problem in the solution and not being
really held on to their viewpoint only
also like overall product management as
the company grows and different
companies are different about this but
in a lot of larger companies the role of
a product manager is also having the
being the ear on the ground for the team
to understand what's happening across
the company if it needs other teams to
help do something to get your product
launched then being able to like you
know for a lack of a better term
negotiate that that gets picked up in
that roadmap and being able to explain
the same aspect of why this is important
for the other team to do for the company
and for also it's how it aligns to the
larger goal of their team so there's a
lot of soft skills and a lot of
back-and-forth conversation that is
conversation skills that are required in
general and understanding how people are
motivated and teams are motivated to
drive along along the same path for the
same vision many product managers are
from engineering they may have been core
contributor or
individual contributor at some time what
kind of pitfalls with that particular
career path what rather not pitfalls but
difficulties might somebody have when
they transfer from from an engineering
purely engineering role into a product
management position yeah actually I had
the similar roles so I can walk you
through my experience um so the biggest
things I think actually some of the best
park managers or ex engineers and I
think the reason for that is because
some of the things that a non-technical
non non engineering product manager
might face is the not under it's not
understanding what goes into building a
product watch but something that might
seem very simple on the front end from
an experience perspective might require
quite a bit of complex setup in the back
end and usually you see this
conversation go pretty poorly when
people say like a product manager might
be saying like hey it's so simple it's
like two pages in two clicks why does it
take so much time or that company can do
this and they launch it faster than us
like what's what's going on like you
know and that that basically shows that
the program at is not understanding in a
lot of cases shows that man is not
understanding the nuances of what's
problematic or tough to do in the
technology infrastructure of that
specific company or product so I think
having a technical background definitely
helps you get closer get a closer
understanding and of what it takes to
build but also helps you be in the good
strides of the engineering counterparts
who are going through the process of
building in that specific infrastructure
the flip side to this is if you move
from engineering to product management
and you are now helping by the some of
these conversations you have to be
careful to not be very prescriptive to
your engineering team because just
because you did it before and you would
do it in a certain way that doesn't mean
that that's exactly the way that the
team thinks that they should be
implementing those changes to so the
first thing I would say is while it's
good to know how your product and system
works you need to be careful that you
actually to pull yourself out of this
specific implementation details on a day
to day basis as time goes by because
technology stacks evolved technology
products evolve
so what might have been true if you move
from a engineering individual
contributor role into a product
management role what might have been
true on day one day two of you moving
system might have evolved in six months
that it might not be as true anymore and
nobody really likes to be told how to do
their jobs it's the it's better to be
operating at a higher level and helping
the dream team move on prioritization
and making sure they understand the
vision the why and the how sorry the
what and the wife but the way they can
help team is by asking the right
questions so it's fine to ask hey I
remember this part of the sack was built
this way could we have this in the
shorter term could we do X Y and Zed
shortcut if needed because we really
really need to try and learn and test
but then come back and fix this as
opposed to just saying why don't you
just go and do this I know this part of
the code this out should be done there's
a nuance there so I think that's very
true for early product managers will
move from engineering to product and
then also if you are stuck in
engineering trying to go all the way
deep into the implementation you only
have X hours in a week to work so how
are you helping the team with the other
stuff that we talked about earlier about
understand the customer the analytics
prioritization cross teamwork all of the
stuff is being dropped properly you're
not spending as much time on it because
used to stuck in part of the code to try
and figure out how to best implement
this yeah that's a good point it might
be easier for those of us that come from
engineering to kind of slaver our
product management style with too
heavily with with engineering focus
stuff in and neglect the interaction
with customers finding customers
facilitating their conversations with
the engineering team that can that can
go undone yes and I'm in general like
engineers and technologists in general
tend to be more solutions focused so
given a problem we try to like gravitate
towards a solution and the whole premise
of product management is to continue to
go down the rabbit hole of why and what
more than how and if you stick to the
how more they need basically not doing a
helpful service to your team so how
should a product manager
judge or measure the success of
themselves how should
team what expectations should the team
have of the product manager so I think
the way I think about this is for most
good teams
you know teams rise and fall or like in
a succeed or fail together but some when
I see create product managers if you're
the product owner tend to take the big
trees where it's a team effort and they
tend to take to flame a little bit on
themselves unlike you know and not just
because they should be the fall guy but
more around in the leader in the team
and being able to articulate and do
retros and be able to point as to what
could have been done differently as
opposed to expecting the team to just
figure that out themselves and I think
that's very very important if you look
at really good product leaders they tend
to have this thing in common where the
success is always goes to the team
executing well and understanding the
problem that is solving and shipping
something that is really loved by the
users around the success criteria I
think if you take that into
consideration if you have if you have
the team is learning faster and if his
team is like being able to iterate and
get more feedback from the customers and
improve the product faster then if they
did not have the product manager in the
team that is a very very big sign that
the product might just being successful
so how do you get learnings as quickly
as possible and actionable learnings as
quickly as possible is another way that
I I think product teams value and
measure the success of a product manager
and of course not one person doesn't
make the team so if because the team has
to be willing to go through the process
of actionable learnings and iteration
but given all the different elements of
building a product in a product team
you'll usually have designers who look
at making use of flows very very nice
and beautiful and usable and making a
rich user experience you have got
engineers who think about architecting a
really scalable extendable system and
you've got customer support folks you've
got who keep running great service
you've got all these different functions
the product manager kinda is the bridge
or the glue between all these functions
and they tend to be the person who is
carrying the vision and making sure that
the entire machine is running and
keeping the main goal in mind of which
metrics they're moving how they're
moving it and making sure the teams
focused and not getting too nattily
bogged down in their own domains so if
eventually team gets to the point where
they're having these actionable
learnings and really moving customer
metrics a lot of credit does go back to
the product manager implicitly within
the team because the product manager is
helping the team succeed in one final
question a parting thought what would
you say is the single most important
aspect of product management as a
disciplined Wow I think it is about
enabling the team inspiring the team
enabling the team to learn and iterate
fast and then getting out of the way yes
sounds of course of that success of a
product manager is not necessarily the
right perspective but perhaps that what
it's going to be successful is going to
have the team be successful the team
becomes more enabled more empowered more
efficient more capable exactly yeah
exactly the success of the product
manager like any other leader in any
other company organization is if the
team successful that they're successful
hence when I say you know inspire maybe
they inspire defined bring the customer
voice help the team iterate and learn
and as they go along that process as
they'll become the self learning machine
and they can do this stuff by themselves
you can get out of the way and go on to
do something else and inspire another
team inspire and solve another problem
well thank you very much for joining us
harsh I really appreciate your your time
and your input thank you for having me
Brian I missed week this is Brian arrow
for software engineering radio thanks
for listening SC radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SD - radio death
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us at team at SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of SU
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening